Norman P. Mason Papers
Norman P. Mason Papers
1953-1963
Mason, Norman P.
12 linear ft.
Commissioner, Federal Housing Administration. Collection contains correspondence, subject files, printed material, clippings, photographs, press releases.
3164207
Biographical History
Norman P. Mason (1897-?) was an American lumber dealer and government official from Chelmsford, Massachusetts. In 1954 he was appointed commissioner of the Federal Housing Administration (FHA), and in that position, according to an article in Time magazine (26 Jan 1959), he "cleaned up the FHA, went on to speed up and expand its loan program, started a housing program for old folks, worked hard for urban renewal and better quality houses for home buyers." In 1959 he was named by President Eisenhower to head the Housing and Home Finance Agency.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Norman P. Mason Papers contain correspondence, subject files, printed material, clippings, photographs, press releases from Mason's years working for the government in various capacities related to housing.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection has received minimal processing and remains in original order. The inventory below is a simple box list.
Subject and Genre Headings
Politics, government and public administration; Mason, Norman P.; United States. -- Federal Housing Administration.; United States -- Officials and employees.; Federal aid to housing -- United States.; Housing -- United States -- Finance.; Awards.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Essays.; Photographs.; Reports.; Speeches (documents); Government employees.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Norman P. Mason, 1963-1970.
Inventory
- Subejct files
  - Housing consultant, 1963; letters, carbons, 2 pictures (Box 1)
  - Morris Milgram, Modern Community Developers Inc., 1961; correspondence (Box 1)
  - Gov. Charles Chaffee, R.I., 1963; correspondence (Box 1)
  - Brookings Institution, 1962; correspondence (Box 1)
  - Chicago, Kent College of Law, 1963; correspondence (Box 1)
  - Cleveland Metro. Housing Authority and other companies, 1961-1963; correspondence (Box 1)
  - Karl L. Falk, 1962; correspondence (Box 1)
  - Correspondence relating to new position as housing consultant, incl. Alliance of Progress letter/reply, 1961; correspondence (Box 1)
  - Manuals, "Housing and Home Finance Agency" and "Federal Housing Administration Organization, Programs and Operations" (Box 1)
  - HHFA Data Book (Box 1)
  - Report on government housing policies and program hearings, study of international housing (Box 1)
  - FHA apopintment commission (Box 2)
  - "Housing record of the Eisenhower administration, 1953-1960" (Box 2)
  - Central Savings Bank (Box 2)
  - Clippings, Mason's departure in 1961, misc. other topics (Box 2)
  - Congratulations on position as housing consultant (Box 2)
  - National Civil Service League (Box 2)
  - Address to Federal Savings League, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Monograph on housing financing, Senate Banking and Currency Commission (Box 2)
  - Treatise, "The Total Enterprise Concept," by Donkeny and Daniels (Box 2)
  - Guest register, 1955-1960 (Box 2)
  - Fitness of American Youth, report by the President's Council, 1959 (Box 2)
  - U.S. Government Organization Manual, 1960-1961 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, outgoing, alpha by recipient, carbons; most in response to letters of congratulation on appointment as FHA administrator; 7 folders (Box 3)
  - Personnel papers as FHA Commissioner, 1954; 1960,; undated; copies of designation letters from Eisenhower, statement of acceptance, more (Box 3)
  - Personal correspondence, 1960 (Box 3)
  - Mason, personal stories (Box 3)
  - Mason, re. outside interests, resignation letters, etc. (Box 3)
  - Addresses, 1954-1955; bound volume (Box 4)
  - Addresses, 1956-1961; bound volume (Box 4)
  - Public statements, 1959-1961; bound volume (Box 4)
  - Nomination as FHA administrator, HHFA, 1959; carbons of replies (Box 5)
  - Biographical sketch of Mason, U.S. Housing Administrator (Box 5)
  - Mason, newspaper clippings, 1959 (Box 5)
  - Mason, miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Congratulatory letters, carbons of replies, 1954; 5 folders (Box 5)
  - F. Stuart FitzPatrick Memorial Award, 1960; congratulatory letters and replies (Box 5)
  - Report, Mason to Gen. W. B. Persons, Assistant to the President, re. Dr. Weaver, 5 Jan 1961 (Box 5)
  - Congratulatory letters, carbons of replies, 1954 (Box 5)
  - Essay by Mason, "The Conquest of the Air", Jun 1912 (Box 6)
  - Congratulatory letters and a "Salute to Eisenhower", 1954 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, formal dinner menus, copy of Time magazine, 21 Sep 1958 (Box 6)
  - Notebook, Mason, personnel file (Box 6)
  - Tape recording, "Nationwide Capitol Assignment", 14 Jul 1959 (Box 6)
  - Plaque, "Honorary Citizen of Jacksonville, Florida", May 1958 (Box 6)
  - Photo album, "A memento of N. Mason's years as Housing Commissioner and Labor Administrator in the U.S. Government Washington D.C. April 1954 - January 1966" (Box 6)
  - Views and opinions on Norman P. Mason (Box 7)
  - "Housing record of the Eisenhower administration, 1953-1960", summary (Box 7)
  - "Platform Text of the GOP on Housing and Health: Approaches to the Problem" by N. Mason, outline of Democratic platform in regards to housing (Box 7)
  - National Diary, 1959 (Box 7)
  - National Diary, 1960 (Box 7)
  - FIABCI (Box 7)
  - A Study of Housing Programs and Policies (Box 7)
  - Views on Reduction of Housing [illegible] (Box 7)
  - The FHA Story, summary (Box 7)
  - Reports to the Subcommittee on Housing of the Senate Banking and Currency Committee (Box 7)
  - Book and correspondence relating to FHA appreciation party for Mason, held Feb. 5, 1959 at the Carlton Hotel (Box 8)
  - Photographs and certificate of appreciation form the National Academy of Science and National Research Council (Box 8)
  - Program, "Dinner with...", 27 Jan 1960 (Box 8)
  - "Tribute of Appreciation" from G. girls (Box 8)
  - Appointments (Box 9)
  - Swearing-in ceremonies (Box 9)
  - FHA 25th Anniversary (Box 9)
  - Swearing-in ceremonies, retirement (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 9)
  - F. Stuart FitzPatrick Memorial Award (Box 9)
  - FHA top staff (Box 9)
  - FHA zone commissioners, field directors (Box 9)
  - HHFA, office of administrator, VHMCP, CDP, CFA, URA, FNMA, FHA regions (Box 9)
  - Meetings with groups (Box 9)
  - Executive committee reservists and advisory committee (Box 9)
  - Committee meetings (Box 9)
  - Presentation of awards (Box 9)
  - Book I, citations and awards (Box 9)
  - Book II, citations and awards (Box 9)
  - Awards (Box 9)
  - [untitled] (Box 9)
  - Appointments (Box 9)
  - Appointments BKI (Box 9)
  - Mortgage credit hearings, Subcommittee on Housing, Senate Banking and Currency Committee (Box 9)